Bulgaria Subject Files, Inclusive: 1946-2015, undated, Bulk: 1968-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Bulgaria Subject Files
Inclusive: 1946-2015, undated, Bulk: 1968-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
20
Keston Institute, 1969 -
16 A4 document boxes
The Bulgaria Subject Files contain a variety of materials on multiple topics, including religious persecution, religious dissidents, human rights activity, state religious policies, atheist propaganda, and discrimination of Turkish ethnic minorities in the country.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
From the beginning of the post-World War II period until approximately 2007, Keston obtained materials documenting the religious and political climate and persecution in Bulgaria, a country which suffered under a communist dictatorship from 1948 to 1991.
Bulgaria in World War II
Although Bulgaria declared neutrality at the outbreak of the war, by 1941 Tsar Boris III had entered the war on the side of the German powers. The Tsar did not declare war on the Soviet Union, as he feared division within the country. Bulgaria remained largely untouched by World War II, sending no troops to assist at the front. Tsar Boris III suffered a heart attack in 1943 and did not survive to see the war’s end. A long line of temporary leaders succeeded him until the consolidation of communist power in 1948. Bulgaria remained under Soviet occupation from 1944 to 1947, which aided the communist rise and consolidation of power.
The Rise of the Communist Party in Bulgaria
Public opinion against Bulgaria’s role in World War II allowed the rising communist party to take advantage of the situation by executing and imprisoning large numbers of political enemies by creating a “people’s court” in which thousands stood trial for their role in the war. The purge effectively silenced the majority of anti-communist sentiment. Remaining communist opposition was quelled when Western democracies determined that democratization of Bulgaria was a low priority, essentially allowing Stalinism to be established in the country.
The communist party formally consolidated their power in the 1945 election. In 1946, Bulgaria was declared a republic, forcing Tsar Simeon II and his family into exile. One week after the election of a communist majority Grand National Assembly, both the United States and Great Britain formally recognized the new communist regime. The Grand National Assembly enacted the Dimitrov Constitution on December 4, 1947, which was modeled after the constitution of the Soviet Union and established a formal communist structure in Bulgaria.
The Bulgarian government saw a rapid succession of leaders in the early years of the regime until Vulko Chervenkov took power and implemented Stalinism, including rapid industrialization, forced collectivization of agriculture, heavy reliance on the police and security apparatus, and isolation from countries outside the Soviet bloc. After Stalin’s death in 1953, Chervenkov yielded power to an up and coming member of the communist party, Todor Zhivkov. In 1956, Zhivkov began the open de-Stalinization of Bulgaria, which included the release of thousands of political prisoners and the moderation of economic policies in order to raise the standard of living.
The End of Communist Rule in Bulgaria
Todor Zhivkov became prime minister in 1962 and remained in power until 1989. During his rule, Bulgaria and the Soviet Union created extremely close political and economic ties. Zhivkov’s policies stressed the importance of science and technology, bringing the Bulgarian economic sector out of agriculture and into industry and service sectors. “Bulgarization” was a major movement during Zhivkov’s rule and encouraged larger families and the assimilation of Turkish minorities. Assimilation included discontinuing Turkish publications and forcing ethnic Bulgarian Turks to adopt Bulgarian names. In 1989, the Turkish government allowed the Bulgarian border to reopen so that Turkey could accept Turkish refugees fleeing persecution. More than 300,000 ethnic Turks fled or were forced out of Bulgaria and into Turkey.
Mikhail Gorbachev’s reforms of glasnost and perestroika in the late 1980’s greatly impacted Bulgaria. Bulgarians began to push for further economic openness and government reform. An increase in Bulgarian dissidents, a declining economic situation, and internal party rivalries led Zhivkov’s colleagues to force his resignation on November 10, 1989. He was later tried, sentenced, and imprisoned for embezzlement. Bulgaria held free elections in 1990, and the communist party barely earned a majority. However, their majority was not large enough to govern alone, and the party supported a non-party member for election as Prime Minister. In 1991, the Grand National Assembly adopted a new constitution that established Bulgaria as a parliamentary republic, effectively ending complete communist rule.
Religion under Communist Rule
Exarch Stefan, head of the Bulgarian Orthodox Church, resisted government efforts to control church activities. He left office in 1948 and retired to a monastery under mysterious circumstances. His replacement allowed complete governmental control over religious activities, including legislation passed in 1949 that allowed state supervision for all religious orders. After the implementation of the legislation, 15 pastors from evangelical Protestant churches were arrested, tried, and executed for espionage and other alleged crimes. Soon after, a number of Bulgarian Catholic clergy were tried for spying for the Vatican and for disseminating anticommunist propaganda. Among the executed was Bishop Evgeny Bosilkov, beatified by the Vatican in 1998.
Scope and Content
Bulgaria subject files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, handwritten notes, correspondence, research papers, manuscripts, church and secular publications, reports on issues of religion and atheism and religious dissidents in Bulgaria, and Keston News Service publications.
The materials cover a period from 1946 to 2006 with the bulk from 1968 to 1989. The most notable topics include, but are not limited to, discrimination of Turkish ethnic minorities, Bulgarian Communist Party activity, and traditional Bulgarian culture within the communist state.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received most of the Bulgaria materials in files organized by specific categories and denominations. This original filing system has been preserved. The Bulgaria materials received by the Keston Center in no particular order are arranged thematically and chronologically.
The Bulgaria Subject Files are arranged in two series: I. General and II. Denominational materials. The Denominational materials are in progress.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 20.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
John Paul II, Pope, 1920-2005.; Zhivkov, Todor.
Subjects (Organizations)
Bŭlgarska pravoslavna t︠s︡ŭrkva.
Places
Bulgaria -- Church history -- 20th century.; Bulgaria -- Ethnic relations.
Subjects
Church and State -- Bulgaria.; Communism and Christianity -- Bulgaria.; Freedom of religion -- Bulgaria.; Human rights -- Bulgaria.; Labor camps.; Liberty of conscience -- Bulgaria.; Macedonian Question.; Persecution -- Bulgaria.; Political prisoners -- Bulgaria.; Religion and state — Bulgaria.; Turks -- Bulgaria.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Publications.; Records (Documents)
- General, 1946-2015, Undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  General Bulgaria subject files contain materials on religious persecution, human rights activity, state religious policies, atheist propaganda, communist ideology, publications, reports, Bulgarian culture, society, and dissident activity.
  - History. General, 1970-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Individuals, 1975-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - State. Government. Nationhood, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Census. Population, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Nationalism. National Identity, 1977-1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Minorities, 1975-1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Patriotism, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Government Elections, 1977-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - State Administration, 1977-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Military Affairs - Defense, 1977-1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Espionage, 1983-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Emigration, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Statistics, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Constitution, Law, Oppressive practices, 1971-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Basic Rights and Freedoms, 1977-2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Law, 1971-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Crime, 1977-1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - State Police Organizations, 1977-1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Prisons, Labor Camps, 1983-1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Censorship, 1977-1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Political Imprisonment, Political Prisoners, Political Assassination, 1966-1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Psychiatric Institutions, 1977-1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dissident, Protests, Illegal Actions, 1977-1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - International Relations, 1964-2015 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - International Relations with Soviet Union and Yugoslavia, 1974-1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Relations with Vatican, 1971-2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - State Foreign Policy, 1977-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Non-Aligned Countries, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Foreigners, Smuggling, Expulsions, Personal Contacts, 1968-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Foreign Students, 1963-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Belgrade Conference, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Helsinki Agreement and Human Rights, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Peaceful Coexistence, Détente, Exchanges, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - International Incidents, 1977-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Territorial Disputes, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Western Reactions. Interventions Pronouncements, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Statistics, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Contacts with International Organizations, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - United Nations and UN Agencies, 1973-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Actions Disapproved by the State, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Defections, 1965-1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Publications, 1977-2015 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Terrorism, 1982-1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Religion. General, 1980-2001 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Religion. Thesis, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Religion. Thesis/Summary, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Religion. Interdenominational, 1965-2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Religion. Church and State, 1976-1997 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Government Body for Religious Affairs, 1985-1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Religion and Law, 1976-2004 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Religion and Law Manuscript, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Religious Freedom, 1983-2003 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - State of Religious Freedom, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Religious Liberty, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Religion and Science, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Religion and Peace, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Religion Abroad, 1970-1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sociology of Religion, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Oppressive Practices, 1970-1990 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Trials of Believers, 1949-1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Imprisonment of Believers, 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Sects and Religious Minorities, 1963-1998 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Monasticism and Monasteries. Interdenominational, 1963-1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Missions, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Missions Abroad, 1998-2000 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Theological Education. Interdenominational, 1985-1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Religious Statistics, 1965-1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Ecumenical Movement, 1971-2006 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - World Council of Churches, 1971-1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Religion and Nationalism, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Religion and Culture, 1977-1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Bible, 1970-1998 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Religion and Youth, 1978-1997 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Atheism, 1963-1988 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Atheism in the Press, 1977-1984 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Atheist Publications and Books, 1977-1987 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Atheist Museums, Libraries, Exhibitions, 1967-1979 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - New Traditions, 1970-1984 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Scientific Atheism, Philosophy of Atheism, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Training in Atheist Work, Schools of Atheism, Seminars, Conferences, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Methods of Atheist Work, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Atheism in Education, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Statistics, 1968-1979 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Atheism in Theatre and Cinema, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Environment and Ecology, 1986-1995 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Philosophy, 1977-1986 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Ethics, 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Agriculture, 1965-1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Economy, 1975-1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Labor, 1976-1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Crisis and Aid, 1985-1997 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Trade, 1975-1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Education, 1974-1987 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Educational Institutions and Programs, 1977-1992 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Students, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Geography, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Natural Disasters, 1977-1986 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Anthropology, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Science - Space Exploration and Travel, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Health, 1977-1998 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Tourism and Travel, 1962-2001 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Sport, 1979-1988 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Television, 1977-1991 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Press, 1977-1985 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Journalists, Journalist Organizations, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Radio, Broadcasts, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Culture, 1972-1991 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Cinema, 1977-1991 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Theatre, Ballet, Opera, 1985-1991 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Museum Exhibitions, Cultural Heritage, 1975-1985 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Language, 1973-1984 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Culture Trends, 1974-1984 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Literature, 1963-1992 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Individual Writers, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Monuments, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Music, 1961-1991 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Art. Sculpture and Painting, 1963-1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Architecture. Restoration, 1975-1978 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Women, 1977-1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Women's Role in Society, 1976-1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Youth (1 of 2), 1969-1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Children, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Youth (2 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Youth Organizations, World Festivals, Conferences, 1976-1991 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Patterns of Youth Behavior, 1977-1982 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Youth Delinquency, 1975-1988 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Social Programs, 1975-1987 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Alcoholism, 1976-1987 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Drugs, 1976-1987 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Bribes, Thefts of State Property, 1977-1982 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Private Possession, Petit Bourgeois Tendencies, 1977-1993 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Family, 1975-1988 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Family and Society, 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Family and School, 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Family Problems, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Marriage and Divorce, 1974-1985 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Parent-Children Relations, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Sex Education, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Everyday Life, 1973-1979 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Superstitions, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Sociology, Social Class, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Visual Materials, unknown (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Bulgarian Communist Party, 1974-1995 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Party Congress, Committees, and Decisions, 1977-1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Bulgaria and other Similar Parties and States, 1971-1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Celebration of Heroes, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Political Shake-ups, Purges, Ideological Deviations, 1977-1990 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Communist Party Statistics, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Individual Communist and Ideologists, 1977-1983 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Socialist way of life, 1965-1980 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Ideology General, 1965-1990 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Ideological Propaganda, Work, Education, 1977-1979 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Ideological Differences with Communist parties in West, Eurocoms, 1976-1978 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Ideological Differences in the West, 1977-1979 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Glastnost and Communist Restructuring, 1975-1996 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Opposition Parties, 1987-1992 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Free Elections and Polls, 1988-1997 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Multi-Party Talks, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Government Issues Post-Free Elections, 1990-1997 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - General Reports, 1965-2000 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Voice of America, 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Keston College, 1975-1989 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Radio Liberty Free Europe, 1971-1978 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - SWB Reports, 1985-1997 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Eastern European Newsletter, 1987-1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - RFE Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - RFE Reports, 1977-1981 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - RFE Reports, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - RFE Reports, 1983-1986 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - RFE Reports, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - RFE Reports, 1983-1988 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - RFE Reports, 1986-1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - RFE Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Le Monde, 1981-1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Kath Press, 1981-2001 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Otechestven Front, 1978-1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Tsurkoven Vestnik, 1975-1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Sofia News, 1980-1991 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Rabotnichesko Delo, 1986-1990 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Evreisky Vesti, 1976-1984 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - DUMA, 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - YACA/ Chasa 24, 1992-1996 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - YACA/ Chasa 168, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Denominational, 1962-2004, undated; 2
  Bulgaria Denominational subject files contain materials on religious denominations, Christianity, Catholicism, Orthodoxy, Judaism, and Islam
  - Roman-Catholic Church, 1968-1998 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Catholics in Bulgaria, 1989-2000 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Pope John Paul II Assassination Attempt, 1882-1995 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Pope John Paul II Assassination Attempt - Rabotnichesko Delo, 1986-1987 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Pope John Paul II Assassination Attempt - Otechestven Front, 1983-1986 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Pope John Paul II Assassination Attempt - Sofia News, 1984-1991 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Orthodox History, 1965-2004 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Individual Orthodox Churches, 1969-2000 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Patriarchate, 1965-2004 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Church-State Relations, 1964-1999 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Orthodox Church Life, 1961-2003 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Orthodox Festivals, Holidays, & Anniversaries, 1970-1991 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Orthodox Services, Rituals, & Liturgy, 1973-1989 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Orthodox Parish Life (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Orthodox Church Publications, 1963-2000 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Monasticism- Orthodox, 1967-1992 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Orthodox Individuals, 1962-1999 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Working and Living Conditions of Orthodox Clergy, 1977-1989 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Orthodox Visits (to or from countries), 1978-1987 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Emigration on Religious Grounds (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Harassment and Discrimination of Orthodox Christians, 1964-1993 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Orthodox Theology, 1964-1990 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Orthodox Theological Education, 1967-1987 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Orthodox Schism, 1990-2000 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Orthodox Statistics, 1969-1974 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Orthodox Relations with Fellow Believers, 1969-1998 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Mount Athos, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Orthodox Ecumenical Relations with other Denominations, 1964-2002 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Orthodox Ecumenical Relations Interdenominational, 1972-1992 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Orthodoxy with the World Council of Churches ( W.C.C.), 1974-1998 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Conference of European Churches (C.E.C.), 1975-1985 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Pronouncement on Secular Affairs (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Peace Activities, 1976-1999 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Christian Peace Conference, 1976-1986 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Orthodox Literature (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Orthodox Music, 1975-1977 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Orthodox Church Art, Painting, Sculptures, and Icons, 1970-1991 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Orthodox Church Architecture and Restoration, 1972-1997 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Methodius and Cyril, 1980-1989 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Orthodox Reports in Other Languages, 1978-1993 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Protestant Church, 1982-1997 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Evangelicals, 1976-1999 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Baptist Church, 1973-2000 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Methodist Church, 1982-1999 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Armenian Church, 1985-1989 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Adventist Church, 1982-1997 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Uniate Church, 1993-2001 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Congregational Church, 1985-1990 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Pentecostal Church, 1969-1998 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Judaism, 1970-2002 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Islam, 1976-1997 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Muslim Ethnic Turks in Bulgaria - Sofia News, 1985-1989 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Muslim Ethnic Turks in Bulgaria - Bulgarian Publications, 1985-1990 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Muslim Ethnic Turks in Bulgaria - International Newspapers, 1985-1994 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Muslim Ethnic Turks in Bulgaria - Reports and Newsletters, 1976-1995 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Muslim Ethnic Turks in Bulgaria - SWB Reports, 1985-1996 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Muslim Ethnic Turks in Bulgaria - Radio Free Europe (RFE), 1977-1989 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Muslim Ethnic Turks in Bulgaria - Amnesty International, 1985-1990 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Muslim Ethnic Turks in Bulgaria- Ethnic Tension between Turks and Bulgarian Nationalists, 1989-1990 (Box 16, Folder 8)